Domain Name System, DNS, is the service of choice for resolving hostnames to IP addresses. Take a look at this DNS setup on Windows Server.
Here, we see a couple of hostnames on the network and their IP addresses. In a Windows environment, DNS is set up when Active Directory is set up.
Or, DNS can be installed as a role on a server that is not a domain controller.
This DNS server you see is an example of an internal DNS server as it is only resolving hostnames on this internal network.
Many DNS servers are external DNS servers, which resolve Internet names to addresses. Take, for example, a simple ping command.
On this device, I'm going to ping www.google.com. Somewhere, a DNS server had to resolve this hostname to this IP address.
There are actually 13 root DNS servers worldwide that have these massive tables of hostnames and IP addresses.
Having DNS sure beats the alternative, which is that you would have to memorize the IP address of every website and host you visit. That would not be fun.
Speaking of DNS servers, to find out what DNS server you are running, run the ipconfig /all command. It will tell you in order which DNS servers are being applied to your device.
Here, I have a couple of external DNS servers followed by three internal DNS servers.
This means that we should have no problem resolving both internal and external hostnames to IP addresses.